welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
all right check-ins
uh feel calm welcome to the stoa i'm
peter limberg
and the stow is a place for us to go
here and dialogue about what matters
most at the nice edge at this moment
and yeah we're at the nice edge
so what's happening today the the
general is here the sense making mensch
jordan hall phil chen our game b
superstar he's going to emcee the day
if you have any questions after jordan
uh
shares his thoughts put in the chat box
um this will
go on youtube so if you don't want to be
on youtube ask phil
to read the question on your behalf um
and that being said
i will hand it over to phil and just
make sure everyone can unmute themselves
all right phil floor's yours
i got me um yeah so just to add some
a little bit more details um jordan hall
who currently is
also named phil chin on the screen here
i feel a little bit weird about that
um it's gonna be here for an hour and
then um
afterwards we will have some breakout
sessions also to try and sense make
on what's happening today um but yeah
i'm super excited of having jordan here
and yeah there's so much going on in the
world
i feel like culture wars are heating up
again and
i'm just trying to figure out what's
happening in different agendas and
the person that i was going to point to
is
jordan hall and that's why we have him
here today
and i'm super excited for that um so
yeah i wanted to pass it to jordan and
for another situational session um
or assessment uh the riot edition so
jordan uh what is the situation
i'm unmuted all right so um i noticed as
i was
i was thinking about this that there was
a desire to go down
into the details and then what i
realized was that's
exactly the wrong approach the right
thing to do right now is to actually go
way up and even i don't know if
anybody's read the
original situational assessment 2017
document but to be thinking if you think
about the architecture of that
it described a series of fronts and then
it sort of talked at the bottom about
the
the deep basis of and sometimes what's
really going on like the deep driver
this
that's causing the various fronts to
show up as they show up
um and i believe i call it the war of
collective intelligence
um so let me give that as the frame
because i think that's the best way of
grasping what's going on
before i get there i'd like to give a
visual metaphor that i feel this gives
you a really solid sense
so um if you've ever seen
one of those stop-motion photographs of
a
rotting corpse you've got a
rabbit or a mouse or something sitting
in the in the grass and it
begins to almost like vibrate and then
it up wells and then it suddenly just
disappears
um that's what's happening and
now the the the thing that is is in the
process
of of decay is the coherence
that was constructed back in the
mid-century
which i named the church so the blue
church is dead and the blue church is in
the process of decay
and and that decay will show up as
something like
a a fractal war not a civil war
because the the basis for any kind of
conflict is is some level of coherence
right if
you have any conflict is obviously
between two kinds of beings some two
kinds of
coherent organizations of some sort
right now the process the problem is
that the ability to even achieve any
level of coherence is
is falling so coherence is decreasing
across the entire field
and then there's a continuous upwelling
of
of efforts to achieve some level of
coherence in that process
and then those forces end up engaging
with each other through all the
different
uh domains of conflict that can that can
happen so if you imagine a biological
organism
and then imagine there's there's
structure like it's actually holding up
like it's maybe a
horse that's holding up a uh a weight
then you imagine the process of decay so
like the
there are structural forces that will
you'll see them move or fall
because the underlying coherence that
had been supporting them that was part
of their underlying assumption that they
needed to have to function
is itself actually decaying and so
you'll see structural stuff move
and that's very salient it's sort of
very easy to see like a banking collapse
like oh my gosh a banking collapse or
you know buildings burning on the street
and things like that
but that's actually a surface effect
a big chunk of actual substructure
happening at the level of the uh
the coherent dynamic that is losing its
capacity to be a weight-bearing load
and but of course the superficial effect
is not meaningless it's very important
because it actually creates and
accelerates
the other dynamics in the in the larger
system so
at the end of the day we all we all
definitely care about bullets and
buildings as much as we care about the
the subtle stuff that's going on but um
so if you can hold that metaphor i think
that
that that will help to help me get to a
level of clarity
so
to kind of recapitulate to to make sure
we're more or less in
a shared space uh the the notion
is that um
you know since 75 000 years ago
humans have been seeking by necessity
mechanisms of achieving a form of of
coherence and i'll explain a little bit
more like a simple way of
what i mean by that a form of coherence
that can satisfy three basic
characteristics
uh one is that it can form a stable
interiority meaning
it can actually hold itself as coherent
with some number of people it can have a
population that is
coherent together um
the second is that it can do so
effectively in the context of nature
meaning that it can actually
effectively extract resources from
nature that can maintain the
the livingness of the various elements
of its of its
coherent humanness and then third is it
can maintain its stability vis-a-vis
other coherent groups of humans out in
the world sometimes known as war
um and there's a you know been a
continuous competitive evolution on that
particular landscape now for
several tens of thousands of years and
and each
phase of that work changes the
characteristics of what's possible
you know the innovation of certain kinds
of technologies might
change the scope of the number of people
that could be actually
entrained under a different field of
coherence so the invention of say mass
media and large long-scale
train ship and air aircraft
transportation
gives rise to the possibility of
actually having something like the uh
the post-war nation state um
so coming into the the end of world war
ii we entered into the field of
coherence that i called the blue church
and so that has a particular set of
structural characteristics to it it has
the capacity and it shows up
both as itself the the thing i call the
blue church proper which is the
anglo-american specific version of that
of that form
as well as uh copies so the you know the
japanese structure is a slightly
different variation on the theme
and is also connected to the more
fundamental anglo-american structure
the german structure you know the eu has
a form kind of a variation of mutation
on that on that theme as well
so and that has a has advantages and
disadvantages
the the advantage of a field of
coherence is that
it more or less is able to exit
most of the forms of conflict that we
would see among
um sort of squabbling humans from its
interiority under the under the
mechanisms of
order and policing and by order what i
mean is people will choose to do things
like engage in transactions or just kind
of like yell at each other across the
fence
rather than escalating into higher
levels of conflict and policing is that
when high levels of conflict do emerge
the in this case the state has the
capacity to deploy
asymmetric power to extinguish that
conflict um
which of course has all kinds of
slippage and disproportionate
uh effects uh across the social field
but net net
um there's a uh a stability an inability
of the
of any particular subset of groups to
exit meaningfully
or to defect catastrophically
and of course the disadvantages are that
it has a particular distribution it has
a certain signature characteristic and
it creates a niche
it creates a an internal ecosystem that
creates
um winners and losers of certain sorts
based upon
a wide variety of characteristics that
have to have to do with the specifics of
that particular
moment it's technological
characteristics it's historical
path dependencies its um even its
geographic
characteristics um okay so
we then move into a moment where the the
deep basis
the the primary mechanisms that maintain
the integrity
of that particular kind of coherence
that stuff starts to actually break down
and there's there's sort of three
primary reasons
one is for example a change at the level
of techne
so the possibilities of technology shift
enough that the the things that had been
um both necessary and sufficient like
for example broadcast television's
capacity to create a shared
meta-narrative
um certainly find themselves no longer
necessary nor sufficient
the internet's capacity to decimate
that effort to create a controlled
shared metanarrative and generate a very
large number of micro narratives that
can now actually in fact out-compete the
meta-narrative's efforts to create a
here's the what's one story of what is
true so that's one example
and of course you can kind of identify
all the different vectors of technology
that
that exists you know pick your poison um
the second is uh uh corruption
of course which we're experiencing ad
nauseam so and in
in the context of corruption the
metaphor of like
when you land at heathrow airport and
you see
how dirty it is and you see how
hard it is to maintain
well-functioning complicated systems
in the context of actual live complexity
over any period of time
right this is atherosclerosis but what i
mean by corruption i don't necessarily
mean just
you know judges taking bribes or or
dirty cops
or i mean what i mean is the whole
milieu of ways that the the mechanisms
that maintain the operating machinery of
the sociology which are all complicated
systems
begin to develop um
[Music]
parasites on top of them or deviations
and how they function generate entropy
that generates an increasing level of of
ripples out into the larger environment
and by the way requires more and more
energy to work like an
old car engine that's kind of um
you know leaking oil and has you know
busted valves
so then the third is is just
obsolescence
obsolescence has to do with the degree
to which the the total systemic dynamics
that enabled that particular coherence
to
provide well functioning vis-a-vis those
three remember
interior nature and an exterior
is no longer actually adequate to the
environment that finds itself in right
either there's a
superior competitor out in the
environment that's now banging on the
outside
of the boundary so for example in the
context of the roman coherence back in
the
3rd century a.d the the various germanic
tribes had been
evolving their own capacities for
coherence and war making
to the point where the actual
effectiveness of the the roman legions
reached a tipping point where its
ability to survive against the exterior
was no longer adequate and you had a
kind of a catastrophic popping event and
the barbarian invasions
began to just pour through obviously
that was also tied to things like
corruption but you can just look at the
obsolescence piece
um or you have things like um
the velocity of communication that's
available
in a digital network environment
operates at
such a faster pace than legal processes
developed in the 1950s can operate that
the the old system of of endeavoring to
legislate and regulate
literally just can't keep up and that's
another example of obsolescence so
one or more of those three
characteristics and generally all of
them
emerge and you know eventually there is
a tipping point
and the the old coherence begins to
break down
and in in the meantime of course what
ends up happening is there becomes to be
a struggle
for the would be just the resources the
energy the human
literally the human beings which is
except the creativity the generativity
um and the the productivity the
application of labor into new kinds of
coherence
that are now looking for a new kind of
uh stability
so if you take that that whole story and
you kind of look at the various lenses
that i provided in the situational
assessment document
you'll notice that each one of those
fronts was really just a lens at looking
at that story right so if you looked at
geopolitics geopolitics if you look at
that lens you can see oh okay there's
this
unconventional warfare metadynamic that
is just
the water right so where we've lived
since mutually assured destruction push
conflict into the into the fractal level
um and of course that's ongoing right so
right now
one of the things that is happening is
that the the level of unconventional
warfare is
escalating significantly right so to
depict the folks that uh
that philip and i are apparently closely
related to china is very active
in unconventional warfare um
right now at a high level like they're
much more so than they have been in the
in the recent past because
now is an opportunity space like lots of
chaos is happening inside their
primary global um adversary
and and so nudging that through
traditional well
traditional and conventional is kind of
an odd paradox but through
unconventional warfare techniques
is happening you know full stop and by
the way it's not you know just china in
some sense it's by definition
every agent who has the capacity to
exercise power at the global
or at the geopolitical level is playing
that game
must play that game and must play that
game at maximum speed right it's always
total war
um and and so you can look at the at the
geopolitical level
and then you can zoom in and say okay
let's take a look at it inside what
would
ostensibly be the interiority of the
united states right where you see a
whole bunch of different
power groups and power groups are power
groups so you've got things like
the mob and you've got things like the
the cartels that have presence of power
inside the united states you've got
things like the fbi
inside the fbi you've got probably five
to seven distinct groups that have
different levels of coordination
among them that have different alliances
with different meshes both interior and
exterior to the law to the us milieu
some of which are highly corrupt and
some substances the fbi that are
directly in
alliance with the sinaloa cartels some
of which are less corrupt
that have maybe a direct alliance with
our political institutions that we would
like to actually
perceive as being both valid and useful
um
and those are in different forms of
unconventional warfare it's crucial to
recognize unconventional warfare is
warfare where you want to achieve
maximum effect with maximum plausible
deniability
if you combine those two things together
you get the kind of the efficient
frontier so the second that you can be
pointed as being the agent
that is engaged in some degree of
hostility you've lost that move
the degree to which you can have maximum
impact on the world and maximum
deniability
perfection right so that's that's kind
of a simple example of what that game
looks like
okay so that's where we are now we're
right now in a situation where the
process of the decay
of the sets of coherence that were held
together by the blue church and all of
its different modalities
are accelerating through
what appeared to have been a a a
perturbation like a major perturbation
effect
vis-a-vis cove remember that that was a
thing a couple months ago
that shifted things a lot but of course
that's predictable
you're going to have five and six sigma
events it's just that they're less
probabilistically
they don't happen all the time they
happen every once in a while but we had
a five
ish sigma event in the context of
the coronavirus and our collective
response to the coronavirus right so the
whole the event is the whole
complex which
pushed a lot of um
like undifferentiated energy through
the the sets of the whole fractal domain
like the macro the micro all these
different subsets
raised a lot of uh like for example
was it never let a good crisis go to
waste well that that phrase was echoed
in sort of like every center of power at
every fractal level
in the world simultaneously in the you
know on april 1st
and of course what that means is that
the the amount of chaos increases is
everybody leaps forward to figure out
how to play the cards
they've been holding back um which of
course breaks down
other kinds of structure right because
you know war has that has a high
end tropic consequence um and then
eventually
in this particular case uh one of the
places where the the
uh the energy spilled out was in the
context of
civil society right so the kind of the
kindling that we had seen
catch and burn a little bit catch and
burn a little bit in the periods around
sort of 2018 and 2019.
i think what like portland had a couple
of charlotte
charlottesville had a couple like that
kind of kindling was out there
and again in some sense a random and
predictable event
occurred that was created enough
uh energy to then catch the fuel that
was in the ambient environment and it
spread through that
modality and okay so then where are we
now what happens next
so now i'm going to zoom down a little
bit to the particular modality that you
guys decided to
code in this particular event the riots
um
and sometimes it's very simple it
fizzles out or it escalates
um most likely it fizzles out which is
to say that there's
there's no particular place for that for
that energy to go
that is linear the notion of protest
like political protest like organizing
and marching and
sort of shouting and carrying signs is a
fully captured political activity like
from the period of the 50s to the late
70s it was an innovation that had
effectiveness
maybe even earlier gandhi and whatnot um
but by the time you got to the early 80s
it was a
impotent structure and then by the time
you get to the 90s it was in fact a
captured structure
so if i'm in part part of the primary
blue church control mechanism what i
want to do
whenever i run into a a a political
competitor
is i want to push that energy into
protest right i want the
the sort of anti-globalist protesters in
seattle to kind of like do their thing
because it
it allows that energy to be released in
kind of like a barbaric yelp
but to actually be very dissipated it
converts a laser beam into a flashlight
and it enables the control scheme to
continue to operate with sort of the
minimum
amount of necessary change which is very
little in fact mostly just a rhetorical
so there's not a whole lot of of
practical effectiveness that's
associated with the particular agenda
strategy or modality of protests and
even less so obviously with riots
they're sort of
just very high random energy but that
high rate of energy
of course could catch fire to something
sideways
so most likely they they fizzle out
having changed things that they change
um
one area that i think is quite likely
and it should be looked at is the degree
to which
what i would call or not what i would
call what the what those people will
call the
the integral people coined a term called
the green mean
and the the
the exiting of consciousnesses from the
modalities the green meme
which is to say okay that thing is done
and it's
distributions of interpretation and
agenda
modes is no longer meaningfully
effective therefore if i've been
operating under that i will exit it
so the exit of those who are entrained
to the green meme to someplace else
which i expect will probably be biased
towards
simply being effective um is one of the
more fundamental
characteristics of what i think we could
expect to have happen uh
by the way the implications of that are
are complex like very difficult to
predict exactly where that where that
energy goes and what the
what the consequences are
which would then show up as escalation
would be something like
um almost like a copycat
innovation so some new innovation shows
up
somewhat randomly but the innovation is
a structural change
which then is perceived and then
generates a line of copying that kind of
follows
in evolutionary theory we call a
ridgeline in a niche
an example i think that would be a very
concrete example would would be
imagine if you had sorry so three images
that i've seen recently
one image is the national guard marching
through
a neighborhood i think in minnesota and
firing
uh riot control rounds at people sitting
on their porches
um so the other image is
just whatever standard image of of uh
rioters kind of running amok and the
police being
blown away like not stopping it and then
a third image which i think i saw
yesterday was like a
no no two days ago was like a bunch of
people in the suburbs who like pulled
their
their trucks like to close the opening
to their gated community or standing out
front of
the guns all right so so
imagine and i'm not necessarily by the
way saying this is a good thing i'm just
saying this would be an escalation
because it would be an innovation that
could then be cut that would then
definitely be copied
so imagine a circumstance where there's
an escalation of the entropic energy of
the riots meaning that the
capacity of the the control structure to
inhibit that violence by overcoating it
with its own
state-of-sponsored violence shows
ineffectiveness so the riots
spread and they spread into the suburbs
out of the out of the cities
and there is a toxinous move
by the people inside those suburbs to
defend themselves
remember the koreans on the rooftops
during the rodney king riots
um and and they're successful right so
there's like a not just sort of peaceful
protesters walking by
and a bunch of people with guns but in
fact violent rioters rushing
and a bunch of people with guns and they
meet right and then in that meeting and
that moment of meeting
um it kind of doesn't matter where it
goes that
moment would be an escalation event
because whatever happens there
would begin to percolate through the
systems
and create an innovation cycle like a uh
an arms race actually specifically an
arms race
um how far that particular sub sub thing
would burn
i don't know but that there's a lot of
fuel in that particular one
a separate um or somewhat distinct
escalation event might be something like
what are called a police riot
um this happened in the in the 60s i
think either detroit or chicago in
chicago
where the you might imagine like new
york you could see something that's
happening in new york
um where the police
slipped the leash of their
political control right so the mayor
says stand down
and the police escalate and in fact just
go to town
and deploy police power now no longer
constrained by the political authority
that had been involved
and this has happened it happens
somewhat often in history and it's
happened in american history several
times
and then of course would be another
massive escalation because one of the
things that's
happening primarily right now is
separation vertically
in the levels of of of the legitimate
legitimate or expected authority so the
during coronavirus for example where the
states
pulled away from federal authority and
began to form
uh coalitions i think they we got like
six or seven distinct coalitions that
have been
safe you know the feds we're gonna
do this ourselves in the way that we
agree to mutually among each other
and that's a breaking of vertical power
um
and then equally if you had like certain
counties in california
went to the government said you know
your quarantines we're
opening up right now right so another
breaking of vertical power
um and so obviously police breaking with
mayors would be a breaking of vertical
power
and that would be that's an important
one because that kind of dynamic that
kind of pulling
generates a lot of
chaos because vertical power is
structurally very difficult to replace
um okay
that feels like that was a lot of words
maybe we can uh rico here
all right awesome jordan um
so yeah i'm gonna announce everybody
that we're gonna be moving to the q a
session um so if you guys have questions
please
drop it into the chat now um just a
reminder
these questions are recorded so if you
don't want to be on video
um and be uploaded to youtube then
you can let me know um if you want me to
read that question
um and i'm going to kick start it off
um in a sense
yeah uh
i think i have a very similar question
to a christian
i was asking um i think daniel
schwarkenberger at the rebel wisdom
festival talked about
um the elections coming up in november
um and how either way
potentially 50 of the population may
actually figure out that
this this whole thing was rigged
afterwards
so i'm wondering like what is the
interaction of what's happening now
with the elections that are coming up in
five months yeah so it's pretty
pretty pretty clear um that the november
elections are going to be
another um a perturbation point there's
just
too much that's going to happen in that
in that context
and and therefore by the way a huge
amount of energy is being focused on
that particular moment so
uh like for in terms of unconventional
warfare uh it's through the roof
at all levels so one thing is for sure
those elections are going to be rigged
um now they may be rigged actually in a
fashion which they still have they're
still real
there may be kind of enough counter
pressure to hold them together uh
i personally doubt it but this is not a
place that i have a lot of
deep expertise or or like inside kind of
talking to a lot of people who are
looking at it more closely um
so let me give a little query what i
mean by that in the context of
unconventional warfare
one of the very first things that you
try to go after when you're
destabilizing a nation state
if that nation state happens to be um
you know a democratic republic as you go
after the elections
and when you go to the elections you
actually your best result
is to own the elections and have them
look legitimate that's your best result
right so if you can actually
cause the population to continue to
believe that they're in a democracy when
in fact they're not you control what
happens
the second best result is to have them
be illegitimate and therefore
break down the capacity of the
governance system to operate
right so that would be the the objective
of any agency that's trying to
destabilize
uh any democratic republic okay well
clearly our particular electoral system
is sort of with its jugular exposed to
that kind of an attack
and that kind of attack is sort of being
pressed right now and that's very
important to remember like it's
if you i don't know if you guys recall
there's this whole sort of notion of the
russians interfering with the election
back in 2016.
and the answer is of course and everyone
else was too
but it's important to recognize that in
the context of interfering with the
elections
if i'm the russians i'm more interested
in destabilizing the the the polity that
i am and necessarily trying to get a
particular agent
on board unless i happen to really
really own a particular agent which
happens sometimes but not that commonly
in a large in in a large context
so that's one thing second thing is to
recognize that the elections
are multi-layered so we sometimes and i
think this is by the way a massive judo
error
sometimes collapse the election
[Music]
to the election of the of the chief
executive
and so they say oh that's the election
but important in fact like the dog
catcher is also going to be elected on
that same ballot
and a lot of the local elections are
actually more important because they
have a lot more uh
subtle important power so
uh gaming or or shifting or reshaping
the legitimacy of the presidential
election is one piece but actually
to the degree to which you can actually
own things like you know police
commissioners county commissioners
sheriffs that kind of thing then you're
really getting into the
kind of the metabolism not just the kind
of the brain center
of a democratic republic
so in that context where i would say at
least from my perspective
um it's kind of funny there's a hundred
percent certainty that the presidential
election will be illegitimate
it's already already baked in i don't
think anybody believes that either of
the candidates is vaguely legitimate
um and so no matter what happens it's
already sort of that's done it's almost
like the work of making that
illegitimate was
baked in at least months ago
um and probably longer now
and then so once you say like jeez
whoever wins everybody's like what the
hell just happened there and by the way
i mean everybody no nobody's happy
either way
except for a very tiny tiny fraction of
people um
so then the bigger questions and also is
there a capacity and desire to point
at and generate a cognitive dissonance
armored story around the
full illegitimacy of the election right
the
the full rejection right so one is kind
of like a
passive oh this is definitely not
legitimate the other one is
stepping forward and it's less about the
degree to which the election is
illegitimate and more about the degree
which there is a coherent capacity to
organize
a adequate number of effective people to
actually promote that
really into the world that's definitely
going to happen
i mean there's definitely going to be a
competition to see if that occurs
and it remains to be seen whether or not
that kind of level of coherence is
possible right now
then you have the things that are going
on deeper and i think that you can
almost like put it as
you can kind of collapse that whole
sphere into more or less two
states one state is
you know is the is the pyramid solid but
the top
is kind of wobbly the other state is do
you invert it and the whole pyramid is
wobbly
um if there's a very deep felt sense
that
the the whole election process like the
notion that the democracy itself is no
longer
functional um then you've entered into a
massive
phase transition um
if if not if there's still a deep felt
sense that
that it's a uh still a struggle to
figure out how to win
in through roughly ordinary politics uh
then we're sort of still where we are
um and the and the can the decay
continues across all dimensions
okay i hope that was even it was
somewhat useful in the context of that
question
sure i think a lot of people think of
just the presidency
um but a lot of local elections are
where a lot of the power is
gained so ah civilizational consequences
right so that's um the other piece of it
just think about in terms of the
the bigger picture the bigger story um
oh
jesus oh see
well let me back up obviously
one of the things that's happening here
is i'm largely presenting my frame right
so
to degree which that's helpful great
which is not helpful just
throw it away so within the context of
my frame
we are very much in a moment
of of civilization level
transition and in fact i think i've said
it publicly a few times
from my perspective we're like at the
moment of the transition
at the level that gave rise to
civilization as a thing so we're not
like going from
rome to the middle ages uh we're going
from pre-agriculture to agriculture or
more
right and in that context it is actually
i think the case that if we end up
in the with the the election scenario
where the whole
pyramid is wobbly i said a major phase
transition
um i think we've moved we will have
moved
a lot into that place so
the liminal war will have become much
higher because
to the degree to which the the
blue church control structure now read
globally
the capacity of the blue church which by
the 90s had entrained
the entire world right the entire world
was entrained to the blue church
to the degree to which that control
structure is in fact
effectively gone right if the if the
united states
falls into a uh kind of a liminal free
fall
then everything's up for grabs at a
global level
and the crisis you know the don't let a
good crisis go
to waste mindset that had happened in
coronavirus
will now happen all the way and
it is my perspective right now it's kind
of looking at it it's been my
perspective for a decade
that at that moment
the system bifurcates right either a
a new coherence finds a way to emerge
that can actually
hold all the energy that's that's in the
current environment which by the way is
a whole lot
right post nuclear um or
there's just a series of what are called
rip stop breaks right
just things continue to break and i
don't really know where the bottom of
that is but it's pretty deep as far as
i've
thought about that a lot i don't see it
any natural place where that stops
we can go to that as well but yes i
think that the
a full destabilization of the
uh the blue church in the context of a
completely demoralized election in in
november
begins the what i would call the end
game like the full
full movement into the liberal war
yeah i'm feeling a little bit sad and
scared i want to bring in
just to talk about maybe some
positive direction i want to bring in
travis
man girl earlier question around
um
so jordan in your assessment are there
any
plausible scenarios where the us slash
the world
makes it out of our current situation of
like continuing escalation
and authoritative crackdowns uh to
another era of like internal peace and
cooperation
or do you really feel like all the
plausible scenarios
have this ship just going down no i
think
there's there there are a few
well two plausible scenarios um
that are in what we consider sort of the
upside
and what's interesting is that one of
the plausible scenarios
is somewhat temporary in the sense that
it
it it's kind of like the the post-war uh
situation where it has a it forms a form
of coherence the by the way will feel
really good and generative
and we'll have a lot of um like
there'll be kind of a golden age but it
doesn't last that long
like it it this has to do with a meta
theory of the way that
uh time is more a matter of bandwidth
than it is of fixed
moments and so basically as the
bandwidth goes up the
period of objective time like numbers of
times the earth goes around the sun
decreases in the lifespan of a
particular complicated civilization
structure
so there's there's likely one kind of
major upgrade at this civilization
structure level that is a complicated
civilization structure
that is is plausible and it looks
something like a neil stephenson's files
concept
and it'll be non-geographic values
coordinated
you know virtuality mediated aesthetic
um
files which are sort of coordinated
structures
that have some level of interoperability
between them that inhibits significant
conflict between them something like
that like something along that
that sort of sensibility um and
that and by the way now i'm sort of
using a whole bunch of different
theories to sort of generate a rough
very rough estimate but that has maybe a
25-year
timeline to it so it's going to be weird
like it'll grow
and then suddenly be no longer vital and
then disappear
in like one human like one youth one
human generation
the second path is is this sort of
what's called a portal pathway an
evolutionary theory which is
single cellular organisms multicellular
organisms
and then suddenly you know a
multicellular organism happens on the
same landscape as single solid organisms
but once it happens it creates a whole
new dynamic right it's a single one-way
trip and now
you know we all multicellular organisms
are literally a kind of single cellular
organism of particular
kind but now it becomes its own subset
so the other plausible path is a portal
pathway to a different domain that is as
different from the domain of what i've
called game a which is to say
the sum total of all possible
civilizations post-agriculture
um as that was from the hunter-gatherer
method right which which i've called
game b
so that is another plausible uh
transition
and the the probability of that
has not decreased at all um because
everything that's happening right now is
sort of baked in like this is what it
was gonna look like
um
[Music]
and then you know i haven't seen
anything happen that strikes me as being
catastrophically reducing
possibility space in that particular
domain like there's
lots of moves back and forth some
positive some negative but it's kind of
still more or less in the same stream
and the problem with probability in my
estimation is not very high but it's
important to recognize that
any mechanism is endeavoring to think
about that is using
toolkits that come from our existing
set of models which means that they
can't really be considered
particularly valid we have to look at
them with a lot of
skepticism so it's
it is definitely the case that i can
identify that as being a plausible
scenario using our current models
but i can't say a lot more than that
thanks and i should mention as a
corollary
as far as i can tell all other scenarios
are short-lived and collapse rather
rapidly
um i'm seeing germain has a lot of
upvotes
recently so truman if that's how you say
your name
can you on you can ask a question
uh jermaine malcolm hold on i don't see
you all let me switch this i can see
your face
some of you might see me as jermaine
marvel or nominee
marvel sorry um let me find my question
yeah the question is to what extent is a
rick rick sorry
to what extent is american racial
frictions a symbol of the underlying
problem aiding america
and to what extent is the blue church a
colonial project
colonial colonialism being a pervasive
game a
tech right
would you say that again i take it
you're a non-video participant
i wasn't very clear at all to what
extent
are american racial frictions a symbol
of the underlying problem in america
and to what extent is the blue church a
colonial project
colonialism being a pervasive game a
tech
uh completely on both counts
but that does not exhaust the totality
of what they are so the blue church is a
colonial project
colonialism being fundamental to game a
like in some sense the whole point of
game a
was how does my interiority consume
all exteriorities that are adjacent to
it
it is a totalizing gaming is a
totalizing game full stop
and then racial tensions are actually a
deeper
basis having to do with the fact that we
had a genetic diaspora
and our particular bands and subtribes
operating in the pre-agricultural
environment
generally tended to spread out and enter
you know and not interconnect very much
generated things like different
subcultures and different languages
and then the ability to form
cosmopolitanism was
dealt with in one mechanism in the
pre-agricultural environment
and a different mechanism in the
post-agricultural environment and the
solution to the problem of heterogeneity
in the context of coherence
has a solution set in game a
many different variant efforts to try to
solve that particular set of problems
and none of those particular solution
sets are
stable
all right thanks jordan um amy can you
unmute
and ask your question
oh hi i didn't expect to actually uh be
unmuted um
i just wanted hi jordan i just wanted to
ask um to what extent
uh you think or potentially think
that the image dissemination um
is an aspect of unconventional warfare
or
are there other aspects of
unconventional warfare that you can talk
about
the the image dissemination
i have to look back at my question i'm
sorry it was a while since i wrote this
hole that wouldn't suck
sorry about that uh can you speak on the
current media cycle of image
dissemination as a potential aspect of
unconventional warfare
uh uh got it okay so there's uh we could
you could think of it as maybe a a
tension between conventional warfare and
unconventional warfare
so as a mechanism for
producing uh a dominant narrative
during the late 20th century we might
consider that to be
conventional warfare and you could see
for example the the eruption or the
interruption of a dominant narrative
during
the vietnam era and then the scrambling
effort to actually
generate effective mechanisms to control
that and maintain
a dominant narrative uh during the you
know the latter part of the vietnam era
and then
the rest of the 20th century that's
conventional warfare
um and so that's the
a primary mechanism of the blue church
control structure
is to to sort of own the image
uh and to present that image repeatably
and
with uh consistency
now in the context of the the
possibility of generating alternative
images
and in fact now this actually has a as a
fork on it
there's the ability to create what you
might call counter images
or different narratives uh which of
course in the context of the internet
becomes willy-nilly right the capacity
to plug that dike
because almost impossible and images of
all sorts can outflow into the
collective
uh visual field by the way also at a
higher pace of evolution which is
crucial
it's not just number but it's also the
ability to iterate them into fashion
which is
outside of the control structure of blue
church mechanisms
so that's one vector and that's um
that can be shaped and will it can and
will be shaped by any kind of agent
that's endeavoring to use
mechanisms of unconventional warfare so
it is a uh
it's part of the basic toolkit like if i
go into yemen one of the things that
i'll do is i'll begin the process of
endeavoring to generate different kinds
of images
and by the way doing lots and lots of
them and finding the ones that stick and
then up regulating those like it's a
different
it's an evolutionary approach in that
mode and so of course without doing that
in u.s or japan i'll do the same thing
um and to the maximum extent possible
what i'll do is actually try to enlist
toxinous groups in the in the local
cultural milieu who
will have a much richer sensibility
around what will actually work in the
local environment
find ones that have uh expressions that
i feel at least
generally tend to shape things in my
preferred preferred direction
and then up regulate those so that's
that's the way
that that normally works but then also
remember the other side which is just
pure chaos
right so unconventional warfare i either
want to to
sort of get things to go my way or i
want to destabilize things either one is
a pretty good result
and so to just generate pure chaos is
useful and literally
of all i can do is just jack people's
attention system and jerk people's
attention system around so they can't
actually engage in coherent effective
choice
making then again at the unconventional
warfare level i've done a pretty good
job
did that respond to your question in any
meaningful way
okay
sorry about that my internet cut off
i am a little unsure what's happening
now i hear there's some silence
um the last conversation ended and we
were waiting for you to do something
else
alternatively peter was was inviting us
into a moment of silence without
saying anything which is a very
commonplace move for him
i like that move
i got a question phil um yeah i was
gonna be like
go ahead pierre yeah okay um
so jordan you suggested that previously
to phil and i about having um
sort of like sense making sessions here
at the store with experts uh where we
get different experts together to kind
of sense make um
you know a certain issue and we're also
thinking of having a sense making town
halls
that we can kind of like prototype here
at the stoa that could be used in a
local setting
via zoom or something like akin to it
and like a stoic news channel where we
kind of like sense make uh
news items um so i just uh
you have any advice or any thoughts
david jones
i said the same thing so that is not
what i suggested
uh it's the exact opposite of what i
suggested almost the perfect
inverse what i suggested was a practice
whereby a group of people
did two things simultaneously on the one
hand
there was a probably asynchronous and
probably text-based
effort to engage in a collective inquiry
to discern the questions that seem to be
the most meaningful
which would probably take over a period
of time so imagine in this particular
chat there was actually
an ongoing conversation and some
mechanism to among the entire groups to
say okay here are the set of questions
that are the most meaningful
that's one piece of the story the other
piece of the story would then be to
enlist from the body from the from the
group
and potentially from from the whole
population
who do we collectively sense are those
who would have the highest quality sense
making
around this particular set of questions
right so it's
and what i mean by that the key of that
is is much less the
the result of the interaction so let's
say let's just say by hypothesis
somebody mentioned the portal so let's
say by hypothesis a set of questions
came up and they was like yeah this
really feels weighty and heavy
and then in that process there's also a
and i'd really like to see
sort of eric weinstein and um you know
zizek have a conversation about it like
that feels like that's the marriage
made in heaven yes that could be super
cool and interesting
but much more important is the
cultivation of discernment around those
two different activities
that's happening in every distinct
individual right so the discernment of
where is the directionality in my social
field of
high quality sense making in this domain
because there's that
that needs to be cultivated like to whom
will you go
to get better sense making in a
particular meaningful location
is a primary capacity for any possible
future state like
building that into the network each
person has to have a capacity to know
what are the valid nodes like what are
the places where the richness of the
sense making is very very high
like highest gradient nutrition in terms
of sense making
um and by the way it's always going to
be outside of you
by definition that's the whole point of
this thing right collective speaking is
always that so
um and it's never going to going to be
completely flat well sometimes it
might be completely flat it might be
this thing is so chaotic that in fact
the best answer is just to grab a bunch
of
random people and just see what happens
but in many cases there are people for
whom
a particular domain is in fact a place
where their life arc has put them in a
place where their
insight is deep they have wisdom in that
domain and to act to know that to be
able to grok that and sense that
and call them into their place of wisdom
to share that wisdom
is a primary activity then the inverse
of that
is that in every given node there needs
to be a capacity to have a sensing into
reducing the noise in yourself and
orienting towards the most meaningful
every individual must always be working
this is moving from salience to
relevance in vivek's language right
so the collective practice of working
together to increase our individual and
collective capacity
to move into what is most meaningful and
not constantly get distracted by our
salience landscaping which sort of
grabs the shiniest object mostly
rhetorically
but actually being able to settle and
say okay yeah that actually is a
important question that's the places
we're spending some time and energy on
if we get that piece
with more clarity then we can actually
make a solid step forward right
meaningfulness
as one vector and then wisdom as another
vector that was that was what i proposed
as a a useful thing for you guys to
spend some time on
great thank you
yeah um oh sorry and
i used eric weinstein and zizek as
examples
but it probably won't look ideally it
will stop looking like that right that's
a that's an
artifact of a broadcast modality like
the notion that you have
names that you know and they have some
number of followers greater than ten
thousand
is an artifact of a topology that is
definitely not effective
in terms of collective intelligence so
what we would want this thing to evolve
into over time
is a situation where is a much finer
grained level of intimacy
and in fact probably has iterations so
you might imagine a group of 1000
people would form clusters of a hundred
and out of that hundred they would
actually surface from their interiority
the ones who seem to be the most called
to provide wisdom in a particular domain
of inquiry
and then you would actually have each of
those groups would then actually have
interactions so the idea is you actually
want to have this be generated from
within
not a pointing to this notion of expert
the idea of expert needs to be
extinguished
very cool um there's almost a
desire for my side to know um almost
jump in to um
like break our rooms and us all kind of
to try and do some sense making around
the question of what's happening right
now
especially regarding the riots um
and having everybody here kind of
participate in that and see where it
goes
um but i did want to ask you jordan
if you feel like you want to answer
another question
or any final thoughts that you may have
um
or we can also uh do what i did last
time pick someone who we haven't
seen talk before and see if they have
any interesting questions for you
let me just quickly scroll and see if
anything pops
now it feels like everything is is
moving in more in the direction of
breakout session
that's good all right any any final
thoughts before
we break into the breakout session my
final thought is i
i sincerely hope this is the last time
that i'm in this group
i sincerely hope that from this point
forward it is entirely happening as an
evolutionary dynamic happening
peer-to-peer and that i have no
particular special
place like my name shouldn't matter
that feels very sweet thank you jordan
for
taking the time and sharing the wisdom i
appreciated the high level view which
helped me at least ground what's
happening on the day-to-day
with more perspective and i want to pass
it to peter if he has anything to say
before breaking out into some breakout
rooms
yeah so before i stop the record um
just to plug a few events this evening
uh we have uh
kovit and biosecurity preparedness
that's at six pm eastern time it's a
conversation
and travis mann he's having a session
called breaking the frame
travis would you like to go off mute and
just give us an idea what that's going
to look like
yeah certainly so it it's very relevant
to what jordan's been talking about so
we're going to explore ways that
uh our own narratives inside our brains
have been
hijacked and the kind of mechanisms by
which that happens
and start to induce a healthy amount of
doubt
in however we're framing uh framing our
understanding of the world right now
and then also give us the the
flexibility to occupy different
perspectives so that we can uh discern
which ones are most useful at which
moment
beautiful okay so um stow is based off a
gift economy you can check out uh more
of that on the website
and if you're interested in working with
those on panels
with phil and i and possibly jordan to
figure out how to kind of
crack that code and get the right
enabling constraints in order to make
that happen uh feel free to reach out to
us
and uh we're really willing to
experiment i'm doing this as a cyclic
technology incubator here at the stove
so we can test up in the right way
and see what works
that being said i will stop recording
and hand it over to phil
all right